Guide to the Brooklyn, N.Y., Bureau of Sewers records ARC.235
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn, N.Y., Bureau of Sewers records
Bulk, 1880-1960
circa 1853 to 1988
ARC.235
Brooklyn Historical Society
53.5 Linear feet in 87 oversize manuscript boxes, 12 record cartons, and 10 flat boxes
The collection consists of records of the Bureau of Sewers of the city and, after 1898, borough of Brooklyn, New York. The bulk of the collection includes documents supporting the assessments to be levied for sewer projects; the binders of this material include maps of the blocks and lots relevant to a sewer project, lists of property owners, and certifications. The bulk of these materials are from the twentieth century (circa 1900-1960), but there are also many binders from the late nineteenth century. There are a few assessment binders from prior to the 1880s, with the earliest dating from 1859. Other materials in the collection include blueprints of sewer projects and designs, field books concerning special sewer structures, notes on land valuation assessments, journals of work on particular projects, materials test results, and other matter. The bulk of this other material is from the early decades of the twentieth century, up to the 1930s. The latest material in the collection are excavation notices from the late-1980s.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.). Bureau of Sewers.
Arrangement note
The collection is organized in the following series:
Series 1: Assessment Binders
Series 2: Division of Survey and Design Worksheets
Series 3: Contract Administration Logsheets
Series 4: Project Work Logs and Journals
Series 5: Land Valuation Assessments
Series 6: Blueprints
Series 7: Field Books - Special Sewer Structures
Series 8: Tests and Computations
Series 9: Excavation Notices
Series 10: Miscellaneous
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection includes documents supporting the assessments to be levied for sewer projects; the binders of this material include maps of the blocks and lots relevant to a sewer project, lists of property owners, and certifications. The bulk of the assessment binders are from the twentieth century (circa 1900-1960), but there are also many binders from the late nineteenth century. There are a few assessment binders from prior to the 1880s, with the earliest dating from 1859.
Other materials in the collection include blueprints of sewer projects and designs, field books concerning special sewer structures, notes on land valuation assessments, journals of work on particular projects, materials test results, and other matter. The bulk of this other material is from the early decades of the twentieth century, up to the 1930s. The latest material in the collection are excavation notices from the late-1980s.
Biographical/Historical note
In the mid-19th century, the City of Brooklyn made a serious effort to tackle its sewage and waste problems. As with the rest of the United States, Brooklyn (as did Manhattan) lacked underground sewage systems. With the outbreak of cholera and other infectious diseases circa 1830, combined with an ever-rising population, the City of Brooklyn established a Board of Sewer Commissioners in 1857 to deal with its formidable sewage disposal problems. Still, sewage disposal consisted mostly of drainage, and it wasn't until the last quarter of the 19th century that the construction of underground sewage systems began in Brooklyn. With the consolidation of Flatbush and the other municipalities of Kings County into the borough of Brooklyn in the late 1800s, the expansion of the sewer system continued well into the twentieth century.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The sources of the accessions comprising the collection are not known.
Related Archival Materials note
Brooklyn Historical Society holds three photograph collections from the early twentieth century that relate to the subject of this collection. Two of these are plate glass negative collections (Weindorf collection: V1974.024 and Sewer construction collection: V1988.041). The third is a computation book used as a photo album (V1986.247).
Other Finding Aids note
Certain explanatory notes at the series and sub-series levels of the collection do not display on-line in NYU's Finding Aid Portal. These notes relate to the arrangement of this complex collection and related maps in Brooklyn Historical Society's collection. To view these additional notes, the researcher is encouraged to refer to the PDF form of this finding aid, found on BHS's catablog, Emma, available from BHS's website (www.brooklynhistory.org).
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.). Bureau of Sewers.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Cadastral maps; Correspondence; Logs (records); Real property |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sewer districts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sewerage |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Design and construction; Tax assessment |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Series 1: Assessment Binders, circa 1859-circa 1962; 44.8 Linear feet in 85 oversize manuscript boxes, 6 record cartons and 3 flat boxes
  Arrangement note
  The series is organized in five sub-series:
  Pre-consolidation: Includes assessment binders from the city of Brooklyn, i.e., up to the point of consolidation with New York City in 1898.
  Post-consolidation: Includes assessment binders from the borough of Brooklyn, circa 1900 to circa 1952. This sub-series comprises the bulk of the series and the collection.
  Transitional: Includes assessment binders from the borough of Brooklyn, 1898 to 1906. Although these binders date from the post-consolidation period, they were organized in their own sub-series because they do not refer to a local sewer district as do those in the Post-consolidation sub-series.
  Brooklyn District: Includes assessment binders from the borough of Brooklyn, circa 1943 to circa 1962. These binders were arranged in a separate sub-series because their projects were attributed to either a local sewer district named "Brooklyn" or to the borough president rather than a local district, neither case being found in earlier periods.
  Queens County: Includes a small number of assessment binders concerning Queens.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes the documents compiled by the Bureau of Sewers for the likely purpose of establishing the tax assessments to be levied for particular sewer projects. For each project the relevant documents were compiled in an "assessment binder." The documents include maps of the blocks and lots relevant to a sewer project, lists of the property owners by lot, name of the contractor engaged in the project, and certifications about the project and the provided information. There are few technical project details in the material as the documents seem to focus on setting the assessments rather than on project construction.
  The bulk of the material dates from circa 1900 to 1930 and concerns the development of the Bay Ridge, Flatbush, and "Ocean Front" (e.g., Flatlands, Gravesend) districts in the consolidated borough of Brooklyn. Nonetheless, there is substantial material pre-dating Brooklyn's 1898 consolidation with New York City. The earliest of these pre-consolidation binders date from circa 1859, with the bulk from the 1880s-1890s. There are also about 200 binders from the years around consolidation, about 200 binders from the mid-twentieth century (circa 1943-1962), and a small number of Queens County assessment binders from the early twentieth century.
  - Sub-series 1: Pre-Consolidation, Bulk, 1883-1897; circa 1859-circa 1897; 7.5 Linear feet in six record cartons
    The sub-series has three levels of arrangement. Beginning with the highest level:
    1) The sub-series is arranged overall by map designation (Map B, Map C, so forth) indicated on the assessment booklet.
    2) In addition to a map code, most books also refer to a district number and some also further refer to a sub-division number. Within a set of maps, books without a district designation appear first, followed by those with just a district designation, then followed by those with both a district and sub-division designation.
    3) Each of the above segments is arranged in order of assessment book number.
    A few assessment books either had no specified map code, or referred only to the 29th Ward. These are at the end of the sub-series.
    Regarding the date ranges found in the container list, the researcher should consider all to be circa dates. There are several documents within each assessment book, often with a range of dates, and the processing archivist used a single representative date for each book to establish the approximate date range.
    This sub-series includes the assessment binders from the city of Brooklyn (i.e., for years prior to the 1898 consolidation with New York City).
    Related Archival Materials note
    BHS's map collection includes a small number related to sewers from the pre-consolidation period. An especially useful map for use in conjunction with this sub-series provides an overview of the parts of Brooklyn included in particular sewer "maps" in use at 1875. Because this sub-series is arranged by the alphabetical designation of the various sewer maps, the 1875 map of the entire system provides a key for understanding the geographic range of each part of the sub-series. The call number of the map is B A-1875.Fl.
    - Map B (1 book), 1870 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Map C (2 books), 1859 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Map D (1 book), 1871 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Map E (5 books), 1859-1893 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Map F (4 books), 1893-1897 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Map G (1 book), 1874 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Map I, District 21 (10 books), 1875-1897 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
    - Map I, District 21, Sub-divisions 3, 9, 10 (3 books), 1872 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Map I, District 21, Sub-divisions 14-20 (8 books), 1878-1893 (Box 1, Folder 13-16)
    - Map J (5 books), 1873-1882 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Map J, District 22 (7 books), 1877-1896 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    - Map J, District 22 (6 items), 1883-1894 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Map J, District 22, Sub-divisions 8-13, 15 (8 books), 1870-1893 (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
    - Map K, District 23 (2 books), 1873-1894 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Map L, District 24 (21 books), circa 1877-circa 1893 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Map L, District 24, Sub-divisions 3, 24, 26-28, 31, 33-43 (17 books), circa 1872-circa 1895 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Map M, District 26 (1 book), 1895 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Map N, District 29 (50 books), circa 1890-circa 1896 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Map N, District 29 (4 books), 1879-1893 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Map N, District 29, Sub-divisions 7, 9, 12, 13, 17 (5 books), 1876-1891 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Map O, District 37 (43 books), circa 1884-circa 1895 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      General note
      District 37 includes Weeksville, among other areas.
    - Map O, District 37 (20 books), circa 1883-circa 1894 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      District 37 includes Weeksville, among other areas. See especially assessment book 340.
    - Map O, District 37, Sub-divisions 5, 11, 16, 18, 20, 21, 23, 24, 26-36 (20 books), circa 1874-circa 1894 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Map Q (3 books), 1870 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Map Q, Districts, 32, 34, 36 (2 books), 1874-1895 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Map R, District 38 (2 books), 1876, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Map S, District 39 (2 books), 1893-1896 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Map S, District 39, Sub-divisions 1-7, 9-13, 15-21 (19 books), circa 1895-circa 1897 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Map unspecified (2 books), 1859, 1872 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Ward 29, District 1 (7 books), 1896-1897 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Ward 29, District 1, Sub-divisions 5-7 (4 books), 1897 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Sub-series 2: Transitional, circa 1898-circa 1906; 3.5 Linear feet in eight manuscript boxes
    The sub-series is arranged in assessment binder number order, which corresponds to a roughly chronological order.
    In its original state, most of the material was held in hard-cover binders by metal fasteners; in these cases, the material was removed from the binders. The cover of the original binder, which included a project description, was photocopied and included with the retained documents (generally, the retained documents also include a form of this description, but a photocopy was taken in case the cover referenced additional details). Most of the documents refer to the original assessment binder number, but when they did not, the archivist noted the binder number in [brackets] on both the photocopy of the cover and on an internal document.
    Most of the original binders included the date that the material was "confirmed by the Board of Assessors." In some instances, this date was recorded on the inside of the binder cover itself. In those instances, the archivist transcribed the Board of Assessor confirmation date onto an internal document; this appears in brackets as [CBA] with the transcribed date enclosed. In only the earliest binders, another date was recorded, that of "confirmed with Tax Col[lector]'s copy." These were also transcribed by the archivist and appear as [CTC] with the transcribed date enclosed.
    Generally, all binders were discarded after the documents were removed, the cover photocopied, and the CBA and CTC dates transcribed. If the inside binder covers contained any notes other than the dates, these were photocopied. (Some binders noted that the information had been included on a wall map. This note was not photocopied.) Two binders (numbers 26 and 57) were retained as representative samples of the bulk.
    In some instances, documents were bound into their covers. The entire bound matter was retained in these instances. These are foldered together, roughly sequenced with the loose documents.
    Regarding the date ranges found in the container list, the researcher should consider all to be circa dates. There are several documents within each binder, often with a range of dates, and the processing archivist used a single representative date for each binder to establish the approximate date range.
    This series generally includes the assessment binders for the borough of Brooklyn from the years shortly after consolidation. They are differentiated from the bulk of post-consolidation binders (see sub-series 3) in that these do not refer to a local sewer district by name. Generally, this sub-series includes the earliest binders created after consolidation, beginning with binder 1 and extending roughly to about binder 300, though there are gaps and exceptions in the numbering sequence.
    BHS's map collection includes a small number related to sewers. Two maps are especially useful in conjunction with this sub-series. The first, dated 1875, provides an overview of the parts of Brooklyn included in particular sewer "maps" in use at 1875. Some of the binders in this sub-series refer to these sewer maps, which are recognized by their alphabetical designation. The call number of the map is B A-1875.Fl. The second useful map shows the extent of the sewer system throughout Brooklyn as of 1902; the call number is B A-1902.Fl.
    - Binders 1-42, circa 1898-circa 1899 (Box 24, Folder 1-8)
    - Binders 43-79, circa 1899-circa 1900 (Box 25, Folder 1-9)
    - Binders 78-101, circa 1901 (Box 26, Folder 1-6)
    - Binders 102-135, circa 1901 (Box 27, Folder 1-7)
    - Binders 136-168, circa 1901-circa 1902 (Box 28, Folder 1-7)
    - Binders 164-190, circa 1902-circa 1903 (Box 29, Folder 1-6)
    - Binders 187-341, circa 1902-circa 1906 (Box 30, Folder 1-5)
    - Binders 221-300, circa 1903-1905 (Box 31, Folder 1-3)
  - Sub-series 3: Post-Consolidation, circa 1900-circa 1955; 30.6 Linear feet in 71 manuscript boxes and 1 flat box
    Although the binders were found in no organized state by the processing archivist, it appears that the original order of the post-consolidation binders was in sequential assessment book number, which was roughly chronological. These numbers ranged from 1 to circa 3200. In an effort to enhance user access to the collection, the archivist referred to a document within each binder to determine the local sewer district approving the project (e.g., Bay Ridge, Flatbush, etc.). The binders are arranged in alphabetical order by these local sewer districts. Binders referring to two districts are placed with the first district appearing alphabetically (e.g., binders referring to both Flatbush and New Lots districts follow the Flatbush only binders). Within each district, the binders are arranged by assessment binder number. (The first 200 or so post-consolidation binders had no reference to a local sewer district; these binders were organized separately by the archivist, in the Transitional sub-series. A few later-dated binders with no referenced district were retained in the Post-consolidation sub-series as "Unspecified.")
    The districts appear as follows:
    Bay Ridge
    Bay Ridge and Flatbush
    Bay Ridge, Flatbush, and Prospect Heights
    Bedford
    Bedford and Williamsburg
    Bushwick
    Bushwick and Williamsburg
    Flatbush
    Flatbush and New Lots
    Flatbush and Ocean Front
    Flatbush and Prospect Heights
    Greenpoint
    Heights
    New Lots
    Ocean Front
    Prospect Heights
    Prospect
    Prospect and River Front
    Red Hook
    River Front
    Williamsburg
    Unspecified District
    In its original state, most of the material was held in hard-cover binders by metal fasteners; in these cases, the material was removed from the binders. The cover of the first 1000 or so original binders included a project description; this was photocopied and included with the retained documents (generally, the retained documents also include a form of this description, but a photocopy was taken in case the cover referenced additional details). Most of the documents refer to the original assessment binder number, but when they did not, the archivist noted the binder number in [brackets] on both the photocopy of the cover and on an internal document before discarding the binder cover.
    Approximately 1600 of the original binders recorded on the inside cover the date that the material was "confirmed by the Board of Assessors." In those instances, the archivist transcribed the Board of Assessor confirmation date onto an internal document; this appears in brackets as [CBA] with the transcribed date enclosed.
    Generally, all binders were discarded after the documents were removed, the cover photocopied, and the CBA date transcribed. If the inside binder covers contained any notes other than the dates, these were photocopied. (Some binders noted that the information had been included on a wall map. This notation was not photocopied.)
    In some instances, documents were bound into their covers. The entire bound matter was retained in these instances. These are foldered together, roughly sequenced with the loose documents. Some thick or multi-volume bound materials were boxed separately well out of sequence.
    BHS's map collection includes a small number related to sewers. One map is particularly relevant to this sub-series as it shows the extent of the sewer system throughout Brooklyn as of 1902; the call number is B A-1902.Fl. The bulk of this sub-series concerns sewer projects occurring after 1902, so the 1902 map is useful for establishing the approximate extent of the system at an early point in the chronology of the sub-series.
    This sub-series comprises the bulk of the assessment binders. It includes sewer projects done throughout the consolidated borough of Brooklyn (i.e., Kings County) through the first half of the twentieth century. The bulk of the material concerns the local districts consolidated into Brooklyn in 1898 (e.g., Bay Ridge (New Utrecht), Flatbush, and Ocean Front (Flatlands and Gravesend). Areas that were within pre-1898 Brooklyn are also represented in the sub-series, though not as extensively as the newer areas. The specific districts included in the sub-series are listed in the arrangement note.
    - Bay Ridge Binders 204 - 365, 1903-1906 (Box 32, Folder 1-9)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 366 - 479, 1906-1908 (Box 33, Folder 1-7)
    - Bay Ridge Binder 416 (3 vols), 1908 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 483 - 530, 1908 (Box 35, Folder 1-6)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 531 - 572, 1909 (Box 36, Folder 1-6)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 569 - 650, 1909 (Box 37, Folder 1-6)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 646 - 719, 1909 (Box 38, Folder 1-6)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 480, 680, 768, 8--, 1908-1910 (Box 39, Folder 1-4)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 721 - 862, 1909-1911 (Box 40, Folder 1-6)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 870 - 1034, 1911-1912 (Box 41, Folder 1-6)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 1039 -1290, 1912-1914 (Box 42, Folder 1-7)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 1293 - 2154, 1914-1926 (Box 43, Folder 1-7)
    - Bay Ridge Binders 2400 - 2877, 1928-1947 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Bay Ridge - Flatbush - Prospect Heights Binder 411 (8 vols in 2 boxes), 1907 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Bay Ridge - Flatbush - Prospect Heights Binder 411 (8 vols in 2 boxes), 1907 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Bay Ridge - Flatbush Binders 362 - 1019, 1906-1912 (Box 44, Folder 2-7)
    - Bedford Binders 268 - 2549, 1904-1930 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Bedford - Williamsburg Binders 582 - 648, 1909-1910 (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - Bushwick Binders 195 - 360, 1903-1906 (Box 47, Folder 3-7)
    - Bushwick Binders 361 - 456, 1906-1908 (Box 48, Folder 1-7)
    - Bushwick Binders 457 - 797, 1908-1910 (Box 49, Folder 1-6)
    - Bushwick Binders 801 - 1208, 1910-1913 (Box 50, Folder 1-3)
    - Bushwick Binders 649, 900, 1063, 1909-1912 (Box 51, Folder 1-3)
    - Bushwick - Williamsburg Binder 787 - 1232, 1910-1914 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Flatbush Binders 203 - 285, 1903-1905 (Box 50, Folder 5-7)
    - Flatbush Binders 287 - 406, 1905-1908 (Box 52, Folder 1-8)
    - Flatbush Binders 414, 481, 506, 1908 (Box 51, Folder 4-6)
    - Flatbush Binders 462 - 609, 1908-1909 (Box 53, Folder 1-6)
    - Flatbush Binders 616 - 746, 1909 (Box 54, Folder 1-6)
    - Flatbush Binders 748 - 840, 1909-1910 (Box 55, Folder 1-6)
    - Flatbush Binders 507, 532, 573, 606, 608, 842, 1908-1910 (Box 56, Folder 1-6)
    - Flatbush Binders 846 - 922, 1910-1911 (Box 57, Folder 1-6)
    - Flatbush Binders 923 - 1025, 1911-1912 (Box 58, Folder 1-6)
    - Flatbush Binders 1027 - 1139, 1912 (Box 59, Folder 1-8)
    - Flatbush Binders 851, 1086, 1175, 1176, 1180, 1194, 1911-1913 (Box 60, Folder 1-6)
    - Flatbush Binders 1136 - 1237, 1912-1913 (Box 61, Folder 1-7)
    - Flatbush Binders 1240 - 1316, 1912-1914 (Box 62, Folder 1-7)
    - Flatbush Binders 1323 - 1438, 1914-1915 (Box 63, Folder 1-8)
    - Flatbush Binders 1222, 1288, 1349, 1456 (1 vol of 4), 1913-1915 (Box 64, Folder 1-4)
    - Flatbush Binder 1456 (3 vols of 4), 1915 (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - Flatbush Binders 1179, 1377 (2 vols), 1913-1914 (Box 66, Folder 1, 2)
    - Flatbush Binders 1439 - 1560, 1915-1917 (Box 67, Folder 1-8)
    - Flatbush Binders 1561 - 1658, 1917-1921 (Box 68, Folder 1-7)
    - Flatbush Binders 1659 - 2045, 1921-1925 (Box 69, Folder 1-6)
    - Flatbush Binders 2047 - 2293, 1925-1928 (Box 70, Folder 1-6)
    - Flatbush Binders 2294 - 3544, 1928-1930 (Box 71, Folder 1-8)
    - Flatbush Binders 2545 - 2958, 1930-1951 (Box 72, Folder 1-7)
    - Flatbush - New Lots Binders 1405, 1407, 2784, 1915, 1937 (Box 72, Folder 8)
    - Flatbush - Ocean Front Binders 2075 - 2389, 1926-1928 (Box 72, Folder 9)
    - Flatbush - Ocean Front Binders 2473 - 2878, 1929-1947 (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - Flatbush - Prospect Heights, 1906-1914 (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - Greenpoint Binders 1950 - 2669, 1924-1931 (Box 73, Folder 3-5)
    - Greenpoint Binder 2024, 1926 (Box 74, Folder 1)
    - Heights Binders 252 - 1668, 1904-1922 (Box 73, Folder 6, 7)